<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-05-09T21:21:46+00:00</updated><id>https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pablo Padilla’s Blog</title><subtitle>Personal blog, mainly about programming computers.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Salsa practice ideas</title><link href="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2025-05-03-salsa-practice" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Salsa practice ideas" /><published>2025-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/salsa-drills</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2025-05-03-salsa-practice"><![CDATA[<p>
Here are some ideas for salsa dance practice, the main goals are to
train the ability to place the pause at different times deliberately. 
</p>

<p>
During the COVID pandemic I started to get bored of practicing only
the On 1 basic step for inline Salsa. I was trying to come up with
some ideas to spice up my practice sessions and also understand more
about the different ways of dancing inline Salsa.
</p>

<p>
One of the key concepts in Salsa is the pause. My goal was to
see how placing the pause in different beats changes the feel of
the dance. 
</p>


<div id="outline-container-basic-on1" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="basic-on1"><span class="section-number-2">1.</span> The Basic step On 1</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-basic-on1">
<p>
For the Basic steps On 1, start by taking a step forward with the
left foot and stepping with the ball of your foot on beat 1 and the
pause comes in beats 4 and 8. 
</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
  <a href="assets/svg/salsa-on1-basic.svg">
    <img src="assets/svg/salsa-on1-basic-pause-on-4-8.svg"
         alt="On 1 Basic step">
  </a>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-basic-on1-diagram-notes" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="basic-on1-diagram-notes"><span class="section-number-3">1.1.</span> Diagram notes</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-basic-on1-diagram-notes">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li><b>the beat</b>: the first row shows the beat, in Salsa music there are
2 sets of 4 beats, 8 in total</li>
<li><b>home position</b>: the beat 0 shows the initial position, some
people also call this the home position</li>
<li><b>transfer of weight</b>: the red color in the steps indicates where
your body weight is supposed to be</li>
<li>only the <b>ball of your feet</b> touch the ground: the footprints
without the heel mean that you are only stepping with the ball
of your feet</li>
<li><b>traveling foot</b>: an arrow instead of a step shows the direction
your foot is traveling and not touching the ground</li>
<li><b>step on the beat</b>: the X in the last row mean that foot touches
the ground on that beat</li>
<li><b>pause</b>: the Ps in the last row tell you where the pause is</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</div>




<div id="outline-container-placing-the-pause" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="placing-the-pause"><span class="section-number-2">2.</span> Changing the timing of the Pause</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-placing-the-pause">
<p>
For reference, in the On 1 Basic, the pause is on beats 4 and 8. The
goal is now to place the Pause in different beats, e.g., 1+5, 2+6,
or 3+7. 
</p>

<p>
I the following sections I will make the case that placing the
pauses on different beats allows you to get a better feel of
different instrumental rythms; for that I will be using the song
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Nd78Pt6nWb8" target="_blank">
Ay Mi Maria by Bloque53
</a>
as reference for the Tumba, Bass and Piano rythms.
</p>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-pause-on-1+5" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="pause-on-1+5"><span class="section-number-3">2.1.</span> Pause on beats 1 and 5: feel the Tumbao</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-pause-on-1+5">
<div style="text-align: center">
  <a href="assets/svg/salsa-on1-basic.svg">
    <img src="assets/svg/salsa-on1-basic-pause-on-1-5.svg"
         alt="On 1 Basic step">
  </a>
</div>

<p>
When dancing in this style, the forward and backward motions align
well with the TUM TUM of the simple Tumba rythm.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-pause-on-2+6" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="pause-on-2+6"><span class="section-number-3">2.2.</span> Pause on beats 2 and 6: feel the Bass</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-pause-on-2+6">
<div style="text-align: center">
  <a href="assets/svg/salsa-on1-basic.svg">
    <img src="assets/svg/salsa-on1-basic-pause-on-2-6.svg"
         alt="On 1 Basic step">
  </a>
</div>

<p>
You can hear the <i>doom</i> of the base on beats 1, 3, 5 and 7. When I
practice this style I imagine that I'm dancing on the fret of the
Bass; when the pause on beat 2/6 comes, it feels like it's me
sutaining the Bass <i>doom</i>.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-pause-on-3+7" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="pause-on-3+7"><span class="section-number-3">2.3.</span> Pause on beats 3 and 7: feel the slap</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-pause-on-3+7">
<div style="text-align: center">
  <a href="assets/svg/salsa-on1-basic.svg">
    <img src="assets/svg/salsa-on1-basic-pause-on-3-7.svg"
         alt="On 1 Basic step">
  </a>
</div>

<p>
When dancing this variation, it feels like I need to emphasize the
Tumba slap (the PA on TUM TUM PA) on beats 2 and 6.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-other-variations" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="other-variations"><span class="section-number-2">3.</span> Other ways to change the location of the Pause</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-other-variations">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li>you can use the same ideas of placing the pause on different
beats when dancing On 2 and try to feel which instrument is
emphasized for each given variation</li>
<li>two more ways to change the location of the pause is to step on
the Clave beats; for this I typcally need additional
technological aids to be able to hear the Clave, more info in
<a href="#practice-tools">Practice, practice, practice</a></li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-clave-beats" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="clave-beats"><span class="section-number-2">4.</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> Dancing on the Clave beats</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-clave-beats">
</div>

<div id="outline-container-clave-2-3" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="clave-2-3"><span class="section-number-3">4.1.</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> Clave 2-3: Steps diagram</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-clave-2-3">
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-clave-3-2" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="clave-3-2"><span class="section-number-3">4.2.</span> <span class="todo TODO">TODO</span> Clave 3-2: Steps diagram</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-clave-3-2">
</div>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-practice-tools" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="practice-tools"><span class="section-number-2">5.</span> Practice, practice, practice</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-practice-tools">
<p>
You will need some good tunes to practice, I suggest you use music that is
not too fast and song on which the the piano, bass, and Tumba rythms
are easy to hear. I like to use Ay Mi Maria! by Bloque53.
</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
  <iframe width="560" height="315"
          src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Nd78Pt6nWb8?si=q80DPZhByyAnjyhv"
          title="YouTube video player"
          frameborder="0"
          allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share"
          referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin"
          allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>
For the Clave rythm I like to use an app like <a href="https://apps.apple.com/de/app/salsa-rhythm/id379868541">Salsa Rythm</a> or <a href="https://salsabeatmachine.org">The
Salsa Beat Machine</a>, you can control the speed and volume of each
instrument! That has helped me a lot connect each timing of the
pause to different instruments. 
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-conclusion" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="conclusion"><span class="section-number-2">6.</span> Conclusion</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-conclusion">
<p>
Now you have 6 ways to practice placing the pause:
</p>

<ol class="org-ol">
<li>4 positions of the pause on the basic and</li>
<li>2 positions when dancing on the clave beats (clave 2-3 and 3-2)</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>






<div id="outline-container-refs" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="refs"><span class="section-number-2">7.</span> References</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-refs">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li>The step icons were taken from <a href="https://www.onlinewebfonts.com/icon">svg icons</a> and are licensed by CC
BY 4.0</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="salsa" /><category term="dancing" /><category term="salsa" /><category term="dancing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here are some ideas for salsa dance practice, the main goals are to train the ability to place the pause at different times deliberately.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Inherit the Ledger</title><link href="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2025-04-06-inherit-the-ledger" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inherit the Ledger" /><published>2025-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/inherit-the-ledger</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2025-04-06-inherit-the-ledger"><![CDATA[<p>
What happens when the truth becomes permanent?
In a world reborn from war, one vote embeds blockchain into the heart
of governance—changing how history is remembered, and how power is
held accountable.
</p>

<p>
<b>Disclaimer: this post was created with ChatGPT, an AI language
model.</b>
</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
  <img src="/assets/images/inherit-the-ledger.png" style="width: 50%">
</div>



<p>
In 2043, the world finally had peace—but no one could agree on what it
meant.
</p>

<p>
The Cantharan Conflict had ended just five years earlier, the last war
between sovereign states. Ten years of orbital skirmishes, proxy
rebellions, and resource seizures had scarred continents and left
trust fractured. When the Unification Accord was signed, it marked
more than a ceasefire—it was the birth of a new world governance.
</p>

<p>
But beneath that peace was a silence no one dared touch.
</p>

<p>
Until the chain.
</p>

<p>
Amendment Nine sat at the center of the Global Council's circular
hall, projected in sharp light above the assembled delegates:
</p>

<p>
“Mandate blockchain-based public records for all state functions,
retroactive to the year 2000.”
</p>

<p>
No deletions. No redactions. Every memo, briefing, and order would be
cryptographically verified, permanently stored on a decentralized,
publicly accessible blockchain. Interlinked and contextualized by
natural language models. Searchable by anyone, anywhere. Trust was no
longer a requirement—just math.
</p>

<p>
Outside the hall, protest signs floated like lanterns: No More Silent
Wars. Let Memory Speak.
</p>

<p>
Inside, silence waited for history to wake up.
</p>

<p>
Councilor Reza rose. His face was weathered, his voice calm, but his
words carried weight. He had been there—through every escalation,
every classified briefing, every rationalization.
</p>

<p>
“I don’t oppose the technology,” he said. “It’s flawless. Too
flawless.”
</p>

<p>
He gestured toward the projection—a visual blockchain mapping the
provenance of a drone strike: embargo memo to operational directive to
final execution.
</p>

<p>
“But if this passes, we won’t just record the present. We’ll expose
the past. Not all of us will survive what that reveals.”
</p>

<p>
A silence followed. Not of disagreement, but recognition.
</p>

<p>
Across the table, Councilor Omari stood. She didn’t look away from
Reza.
</p>

<p>
“We built peace on a shaky foundation,” she said. “If we pretend the
past didn’t happen, it will happen again.”
</p>

<p>
She activated a simulation. The blockchain interface replayed decades
of locked-away decisions. A natural language model narrated
connections: embargoes, falsified threat reports, unsanctioned
deployments. The chain was verifiable, immutable, and damning.
</p>

<p>
The final node blinked red: The war was preventable. The escalation
was artificial.
</p>

<p>
Then a younger voice joined them—Councilor Eliya, born after the first
orbital strike.
</p>

<p>
“We call this era peace,” she said. “But we’ve never been told how it
really started. What we inherited was an edited story.”
</p>

<p>
She looked around the chamber.
</p>

<p>
“If we want to pass on more than silence, we need to give them
something better. We need to give them memory—verified, unalterable,
shared.”
</p>

<p>
The vote passed. By two.
</p>

<p>
Six months later, the chain opened.
</p>

<p>
It didn’t shout. It illuminated. With full historical input, LLMs
began stitching fragmented decisions into clear, cohesive
narratives. Blockchain entries, once scattered and siloed, formed a
lattice of undeniable truth.
</p>

<p>
The Cantharan Conflict—long a cloud of speculation—was reconstructed
as a precise chain of intentional acts.
</p>

<p>
No more speculation. No more spin. Just patterns—clear, sobering,
precise.
</p>

<p>
Families of the fallen watched the reports not to accuse, but to
understand.
</p>

<p>
This is how it started. This is who turned away. This is why it
lasted.
</p>

<p>
A cascade of resignations followed. Some were prosecuted. Others
stepped forward before their blocks were even examined.
</p>

<p>
One morning, Reza received his summons.
</p>

<p>
He didn’t resist.
</p>

<p>
At his hearing, he stood tall, hands open.
</p>

<p>
“I thought we were defending stability,” he said. “But I see now—we
were protecting optics. I won’t hide from that. The future deserves
better than silence.”
</p>

<p>
He stepped down, not as a condemned man, but as someone who had chosen
to face what he helped create.
</p>

<p>
And those still in power?
</p>

<p>
They began to write differently.
</p>

<p>
Memos became clearer. Rationales were laid bare. The language of
governance shifted from bureaucratic defense to accountable prose. It
wasn’t policy by secrecy anymore. It was action knowing the future was
watching.
</p>

<p>
Ten years later, children learned to navigate the blockchain the way
they once studied maps—because it was a map. Not of land, but of
choices.
</p>

<p>
In her final address, Councilor Eliya, now Head of Council, spoke
simply:
</p>

<p>
“We do not inherit peace.  We inherit the memory of how we earned it.
And that memory is our greatest safeguard.”  No more sealed orders.
</p>

<p>
No more silent wars.
</p>

<p>
The future had inherited the ledger.
</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="shorts" /><category term="sci-fi" /><category term="rag" /><category term="ai" /><category term="llm" /><category term="law" /><category term="plato" /><category term="ledger" /><category term="blockchain" /><category term="shorts" /><category term="sci-fi" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What happens when the truth becomes permanent? In a world reborn from war, one vote embeds blockchain into the heart of governance—changing how history is remembered, and how power is held accountable.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI Career</title><link href="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-10-02-ai-career" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI Career" /><published>2024-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/ai-career</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-10-02-ai-career"><![CDATA[<p>
In 2022, after 14 years as a software engineer, I found myself
reconsidering my career path. The fast-paced software world was no
longer compatible with my preference for deep thinking and
exploration. This post outlines my journey, ultimately leading me to
choose IT infrastructure over AI roles, and how that decision aligned
better with my interests and work style.
</p>

<div class="amzn-disclaimer">
  <p>
    <strong>Disclosure:</strong> Some of the links below are affiliate
    links. This means that if you click through and make a purchase, I
    may earn a small commission at no extra cost to you.
  </p>
</div>



<div id="outline-container-intro" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="intro"><span class="section-number-2">1.</span> Act I: Can Thinkers tinker?</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-intro">
<p>
Working as a software engineer can be stressful. The pace of
modern/agile software teams is fast, bi-weekly sprints, continuous
delivery, you build it &#x2026; you run it, etc.. On top of that, having
to learn the next programming tool/technique is very demanding.
</p>

<p>
I'm more of a thinker than a tinkerer; I like to look at topic from
different angles, do some research, try a few experiments, step back
and switch to something else while I let my brain process what I've
learned, I might or might not come back to the topic depending on my
level of interest or curiosity. My working preferences were not
compatible with my programming job.
</p>

<p>
During my vacation around the end of 2021 I was going over my career
prospects; I thought that I was ready to commit to a role long-term
but I needed to do some research to understand my options and
compare them somehow.
</p>
</div>
</div>



<div id="outline-container-middle" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="middle"><span class="section-number-2">2.</span> Act II: Educated Guessing</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-middle">
<p>
The first half of my career has been writing network clients and
then writing application servers and release automation for the
other half. I felt that I had been doing the same over and over only
with different technologies and industry domains.
</p>

<p>
I didn't feel that I could make a drastic change like going out of
the software scene since writing software was my main activity in
the past 10 years. I am not a big risk taker so I only considered
alternative paths that could benefit from my experience as a
programmer. 
</p>

<p>
I had narrowed down my options to two: software architecture and
artificial intelligence.
</p>

<p>
In recent projects, my interest was often to get a glimpse of
the high-level architecture and I would approach it by studying
the delivery pipelines; when available, they describe the process
each code change goes through to make it to a production
environment.
</p>

<p>
Artificial Intelligence was interesting because it aligns well with
personal interest in the automation of knowledge organization and
discovery.
</p>

<p>
I found two resources that helped me Learn about what AI projects
might look like in the industry:
</p>

<ol class="org-ol">
<li>Chollet's book:
<a name="chollet-dlwp" href="https://amzn.to/3BsKjwK"
     target="_blank">Deep Learning with Python</a>:
the Universal Machine Learning workflow was exactly what I was
looking for at the time, a high-level overview of the life cycle
of an ML Project.</li>

<li>Andrew Ng's content at <a href="https://www.deeplearning.ai/">deeplearning.ai</a>: there I found
descriptions of the different roles required to execute AI
projects in the enterprise world. The site also has tools to
asses your readiness for specific roles.</li>
</ol>


<p>
I was disappointed but not very surprised to learn that machine
learning projects look very similar to other software projects.
</p>

<p>
AI/ML engineers bring their specialized skills to a project and were
I to join an AI project, I would end up in a role almost
indistinguishable to my current role, namely working on the delivery
of AI-powered software to production environments.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-conclusion" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="conclusion"><span class="section-number-2">3.</span> Act III: non-committal commitment</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-conclusion">
<p>
During my vacation I made the resolution to double down and continue
working as a software engineer and become even more proficient
writing code for applications and release automation.
</p>

<p>
My resolution lasted about 4 hours after my return to work. On my
first day after vacation, all it took was to read my mailbox and
chat messages to remind me the many reasons why I was considering a
change in the first place.
</p>

<p>
I started looking for a new role and that lead me into the world of
IT infrastructure architecture. The company is large and for the
past 50 years has deployed pretty much every piece of technology
worth mentioning; my IT universe expanded and I felt quite good
about not pursing AI/ML.
</p>

<p>
If you are considering a career in AI/ML, I highly recommend
<a href="#chollet-dlwp">Chollet's book</a>; it's a
window into the world of machine learning engineering in the
industry, directly from a very influential software engineer and AI
researcher.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-links" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="links"><span class="section-number-2">4.</span> Related links</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-links">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/3BsKjwK" target="_blank">
     Deep Learning with Python</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.deeplearning.ai/">deeplearning.ai</a></li>

<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fran%C3%A7ois_Chollet">François Chollet</a> (Wikipedia)</li>

<li>posts with labels

<ul class="org-ul">
<li><a href="/tag/ai">#ai</a></li>

<li><a href="/tag/chollet">#chollet</a></li>

<li><a href="/tag/software">#software</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><category term="journal" /><category term="ai" /><category term="job" /><category term="career" /><category term="chollet" /><category term="software" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In 2022, after 14 years as a software engineer, I found myself reconsidering my career path. The fast-paced software world was no longer compatible with my preference for deep thinking and exploration. This post outlines my journey, ultimately leading me to choose IT infrastructure over AI roles, and how that decision aligned better with my interests and work style.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Definitions of Intelligence</title><link href="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-09-25-definition-intelligence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Definitions of Intelligence" /><published>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/definition-intelligence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-09-25-definition-intelligence"><![CDATA[<p>
A reference card for definitions of intelligence.
</p>

<p>
This entry attempts to summarize the definitions of intelligence that
I am familiar with. It is the result of trying to organize my thoughts
on the subject. When reading multiple sources from various fields that
address the concept of intelligence, perspectives can
differ. Sometimes, it even seems as though they are discussing
entirely different topics.
</p>


<div class="amzn-disclaimer">
  <p>
    <strong>Disclosure:</strong> Some of the links below are affiliate
    links. This means that if you click through and make a purchase, I
    may earn a small commission at no extra cost to you.
  </p>
</div>



<div id="outline-container-chollet" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="chollet"><span class="section-number-2">1.</span> Chollet: Intelligence as learning efficiency</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-chollet">
<p>
<b>Definition:</b> Intelligence is the efficiency with which a learning
system turns experience and priors into general skill at previously
unseen tasks
</p>

<p>
<b>Proponent</b>: François Chollet
</p>

<p>
<b>Proposed metrics</b>: Skill Acquisition Efficiency (SAE)
</p>

<p>
<b>Perspective</b>: Emphasizes generalization and the ability to learn
 new tasks quickly from limited data. 
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org06bb852" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org06bb852"><span class="section-number-3">1.1.</span> References</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-1">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li><a name="chollet"
      href="/tag/chollet.html"
      target="_blank">Chollet</a>:
      proposes a benchmark for intelligence, the ARC challenge</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</div>



<div id="outline-container-hutter" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="hutter"><span class="section-number-2">2.</span> Hutter: Universal Artificial Intelligence</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-hutter">
<p>
<b>Definition:</b> Intelligence measures the ability of an agent to
achieve goals in a wide range of environments
</p>

<p>
<b>Proponent:</b> Marcus Hutter
</p>

<p>
<b>Proposed metrics:</b> Universal Intelligence Measure (UIM); a formal
mathematical definition summing over all computable reward functions
weighted by their simplicity. 
</p>

<p>
<b>Perspective:</b> Provides a formal, mathematical framework based on
algorithmic information theory to define and measure intelligence. 
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orgc9e97c4" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="orgc9e97c4"><span class="section-number-3">2.1.</span> References</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-2-1">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li><a name="hutter"
      target="_blank"
      href="/tag/hutter.html">AIXI</a>:
      Marcus Hutter's AIXI model for Universal Artificial Intelligence</li>
<li><a name="amzn-hutter-uai"
      target="_blank"
      href="https://amzn.to/3Y3Pa0l">Hutter</a>:
      Books by Marcus Hutter on Amazon</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-schmidhuber" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="schmidhuber"><span class="section-number-2">3.</span> Schmidhuber: Compression progress</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-schmidhuber">
<p>
<b>Definition:</b> Intelligence is the ability to generate novel,
interesting actions or data by maximizing future expected reward or
compression progress
</p>

<p>
<b>Proponent:</b> Jürgen Schmidhuber
</p>

<p>
<b>Proposed metrics:</b> Measures based on Compression Progress;
improvement in predictive models driven by intrinsic motivation and
curiosity
</p>

<p>
<b>Perspective:</b> Highlights the role of intrinsic motivation,
curiosity, and data compression in discovering new patterns and
behaviors.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org74a5243" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org74a5243"><span class="section-number-3">3.1.</span> References</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-3-1">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li><a name="schmidhuber"
      target="_blank"
      href="https://youtu.be/q4fFuZgOZn8?si=Da1V2AUcpl5WorUH">Schmidhuber
      on consciousness</a>:
      intelligence [and conciousness] is a byproduct of data
      compression</li>
<li><a name="schmidhubber-blog"
      target="_blank"
      href="https://people.idsia.ch/~juergen/blog.html">AI Blog</a>:
      Schmidhuber's AI Blog</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-mainstream" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="mainstream"><span class="section-number-2">4.</span> Mainstream AI: Task-specific metrics</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-mainstream">
<p>
<b>Definition:</b> Intelligence is often operationally defined by
performance on specific tasks or benchmarks without a unified
overarching definition
</p>

<p>
<b>Proponent:</b> Various
</p>

<p>
<b>Proposed metrics:</b> Task-specific metrics such as Accuracy, F1
Score, BLEU Score, etc., depending on the task
</p>

<p>
<b>Perspective:</b> Focuses on empirical performance in narrow
domains, emphasizing results on established benchmarks over a
holistic definition of intelligence
</p>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-orgcb4e472" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="orgcb4e472"><span class="section-number-3">4.1.</span> References</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-4-1">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li><a name="amzn-ai-russel-norvig"
      target="_blank"
      href="https://amzn.to/3Y1D9Z8">Russel, Norvig</a>:
      Artificial Intelligence: a modern approach</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-psychometrics" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="psychometrics"><span class="section-number-2">5.</span> Psychometrics: Intelligence Quotient (IQ)</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-psychometrics">
<p>
<b>Definition:</b> Intelligence is the capacity for reasoning,
problem-solving, planning, abstract thinking, understanding complex
ideas, and learning from experience
</p>

<p>
<b>Proponent:</b> Psychometrics
</p>

<p>
<b>Proposed metrics:</b> Intelligence Quotient (IQ); standardized tests
measuring various cognitive abilities
</p>

<p>
<b>Perspective:</b> Emphasizes quantifiable cognitive abilities and
compares individuals to population norms, focusing on human
intelligence assessment 
</p>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-org81127d1" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="org81127d1"><span class="section-number-3">5.1.</span> References</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-5-1">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li><a name="g-factor"
      target="_blank"
      href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G_factor_(psychometrics)">g factor</a>:
      a variable that summarizes positive correlations among different cognitive tasks</li>
<li><a name="iq"
      target="_blank"
      href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intelligence_quotient">IQ</a>:
      Intelligence Quotient</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-superintelligence" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="superintelligence"><span class="section-number-2">6.</span> Bostrom: Superintelligence</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-superintelligence">
<p>
<b>Definition:</b> Superintelligence refers to an intellect that greatly
surpasses the cognitive performance of humans in virtually all
domains of interest
</p>

<p>
<b>Proponent:</b> Nick Bostrom
</p>

<p>
<b>Proposed metrics:</b> No specific metric; concept explores potential
capabilities beyond human levels 
</p>

<p>
<b>Perspective:</b> Focuses on the implications, risks, and ethics
associated with creating intelligences that far exceed human
cognitive abilities 
</p>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-orga73cf4c" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="orga73cf4c"><span class="section-number-3">6.1.</span> References</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-6-1">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li><a name="amzn-bostrom"
       target="_blank"
       href="https://amzn.to/4eJOB1d">Superintelligence</a>:
       Paths, Dangers, and Strategies</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</div>



<div id="outline-container-ethology" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="ethology"><span class="section-number-2">7.</span> Ethology: Animal intelligence</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-ethology">
<p>
<b>Definition:</b> Intelligence is the ability of an animal to adapt to
its environment, learn from experiences, solve problems, and use
tools 
</p>

<p>
<b>Proponent:</b> Ethology
</p>

<p>
<b>Proposed metrics:</b> Behavioral tests assessing problem-solving, tool
use, social learning, and communication abilities 
</p>

<p>
<b>Perspective:</b> Studies intelligence across different species,
emphasizing evolutionary adaptations and ecological contexts 
</p>
</div>



<div id="outline-container-orgd10bb27" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="orgd10bb27"><span class="section-number-3">7.1.</span> References</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-7-1">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li><a name="wiki-animal-cog"
       target="_blank"
       href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animal_cognition">Wikipedia</a>:
       Animal cognition</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-agi" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="agi"><span class="section-number-2">8.</span> Human-like AI: Artificial General Intelligence (AGI)</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-agi">
<p>
<b>Definition:</b> Intelligence is the ability of an artificial agent to
understand, learn, and apply knowledge in a general, human-like way
across a wide range of tasks and domains 
</p>

<p>
<b>Proponent:</b> Various
</p>

<p>
<b>Proposed metrics:</b> No standardized metric yet; Turing Test, general
AI benchmarks, and evaluations across diverse tasks are used 
</p>

<p>
<b>Perspective:</b> Aims to develop machines with general cognitive
abilities comparable to humans, capable of understanding and
reasoning across various contexts 
</p>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-orga8bb605" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="orga8bb605"><span class="section-number-3">8.1.</span> References</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-8-1">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li><a name="wiki-agi"
       target="_blank"
       href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_general_intelligence">Wikipedia</a>:
       Artificial General Intelligence</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><category term="journal" /><category term="ai" /><category term="intelligence" /><category term="definition" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A reference card for definitions of intelligence.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Distributed agile teams</title><link href="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-08-16-distributed-agile-teams" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Distributed agile teams" /><published>2024-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/distributed-agile-teams</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-08-16-distributed-agile-teams"><![CDATA[<p>
Can distributed teams be agile? Does Jira kill agility? 
</p>

<p>
I was scrolling LinkedIn when I saw a picture of Jira executing a
wrestling splash on Agility. It triggered a train of thought about the
place for tools like Jira in the context of distributed teams that
span different time zones and on which the team members often have to
split their attention into multiple projects.
</p>


<div style="text-align: center">
  <img src="/assets/images/jira-splash-agility.png" style="width: 50%">
</div>


<p>
In my experience as a software engineer, I have seen that the words
Agile, Scrum, and Kanban are often used interchangeably. One reason
for this is that the key ideas of each one fits really well with the
others. These ways of work share some assumptions:
</p>

<ol class="org-ol">
<li>Team co-location: everybody is in the same geographical location,
building, or room</li>
<li>Undivided attention: each person contributes to a single
team/project/product</li>
</ol>


<p>
How can distributed teams remain agile when these two assumptions are
broken? Before we go into the challenges that distributed teams face,
let's take a quick look at key differences between Agile, Scrum and
Kanban.
</p>

<ol class="org-ol">
<li>Agile: originated in software development with a focus on
delivery of value through close collaboration with customers and being
flexible in responding to change</li>
<li>SCRUM: originated in software development with a focus on time-boxed
delivery cycles (iterations) with a fixed scope</li>
<li>Kanban: originated in manufacturing with a focus on visualizing
work, managing flow, and reducing waste</li>
</ol>


<p>
The fact that the terms are used interchangeably it's a reminder of
how similar the philosophies are. These ways of working are
complementary and teams mix and match practices from all
of them without batting an eyelash.
</p>



<div id="outline-container-orge7f281d" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="orge7f281d"><span class="section-number-2">1.</span> Documentation as communication</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1">
<p>
The distinction between communication and documentation can be
blurry for distributed teams. Recorded communication can be seen as
extended documentation, at the same time, documentation is a form of
communication.
</p>

<p>
Distributed teams can use recorded communication like chat, email,
comments, etc. to bridge the gap created by geography. As long as
communication is given priority over the tools or processes, the use
of documentation as communication seems to maintain the spirit of
the agile manifesto.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-orgfc7d8e5" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="orgfc7d8e5"><span class="section-number-2">2.</span> Communication through a central channel</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2">
<p>
Some complex tasks require sharing context with multiple people.
Consolidating context in a central location such as Jira/Wiki, makes
it easier to onboard newcomers.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-org935007f" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org935007f"><span class="section-number-2">3.</span> Documentation and context switching</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3">
<p>
Distributed teams are often composed of individuals that participate
in multiple projects simultaneously. Individuals who have to split
their attention into multiple projects reduce the impact created by
context switching by documenting useful details, such as the current
status, and planned next steps.
</p>
</div>
</div>



<div id="outline-container-orgb8fb6f3" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="orgb8fb6f3"><span class="section-number-2">4.</span> Tools don't kill agility, people do</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4">
<p>
For distributed teams, systems like Jira serve as a central place
for coordinating work. I find it intriguing that people with
technical IT skills often forget the value of systems like JIRA and
at the same time they can deliver complex systems. Jira is bloated
and could offer better user experience but it does not impose any
workflow or methodology.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-orgfaa2da4" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="orgfaa2da4"><span class="section-number-2">5.</span> Every project management tool wants to become like JIRA</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-5">
<p>
In principle, e-mail is sufficient. However, once you get used to
the amenities of modern collaboration tools, it's hard to go back
and use only e-mail. Popular collaboration tools seem to be
converging in terms of features like creating a task from a chat
conversation, tracking status, assigning, visualizing tasks and
their relationships, linking to code or documentation, etc. Tools
that started with one of these features continue adding more
features until they cover all the basics of project management.
</p>

<p>
Companies arrive to systems like JIRA by taking a
holistic/integrated approach. It's not perfect, but the available
options are only a round of funding away from becoming like Jira.
</p>

<p>
Project management and collaboration is a complex domain, which
explains why most tools offer a terrible user experience. I always
remind myself that it could be worse, imagine doing project
management only with email and PowerPoint. 
</p>
</div>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><category term="software" /><category term="journal" /><category term="agile" /><category term="teams" /><category term="software" /><category term="distributed" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Can distributed teams be agile? Does Jira kill agility?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Illuminating the Mind: A Journey Toward Enlightenment</title><link href="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-08-09-optocap" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Illuminating the Mind: A Journey Toward Enlightenment" /><published>2024-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/optocap</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-08-09-optocap"><![CDATA[<p>
In the near future, NeuroLight Corporation revolutionized neuroscience
with a procedure that replaced the top of the human skull with an
artificial cap. This "OptoCap" embedded with micro-scale light
emitters, allowed precise control over brain activity through
optogenetics—a technique that used light to manipulate neurons
engineered to be light-sensitive. 
</p>

<p>
<b>Disclaimer: this post was created with ChatGPT, an AI language
model.</b>
</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
  <img src="/assets/images/optocap.png" style="width: 50%">
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orge212275" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="orge212275"><span class="section-number-2">1.</span> The Decision</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1">
<p>
Lena sat in the waiting room of NeuroLight Corporation, surrounded
by holographic displays promoting the incredible achievements of
those enhanced by the OptoCap.
</p>

<p>
"Ms. Torres?" called Ethan, a consultant with a polished
demeanor. He ushered her into a futuristic office and gestured for
her to sit.
</p>

<p>
“You’re about to unlock your full potential,” Ethan began,
projecting an image of a brain onto the glass table between
them. “The OptoCap can amplify your confidence, intelligence,
creativity—whatever you need.”
</p>

<p>
Lena had always been cautious, but the promise of self-improvement
was enticing. “Can it really make me more decisive?”
</p>

<p>
“With optogenetic programming, you can reshape your neural pathways
to strengthen any trait you desire,” Ethan explained. “Imagine
eliminating self-doubt or boosting your cognitive speed.”
</p>

<p>
Lena’s resolve hardened. “Let’s do it.”
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-org440333e" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org440333e"><span class="section-number-2">2.</span> The Installation</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2">
<p>
The procedure was quick. Lena awoke feeling a slight weight on her
head, her cap glowing faintly.
</p>

<p>
“Welcome to your new life, Lena,” Dr. Harmon, the chief scientist,
said as he handed her a sleek control tablet. “With this, you can
select programs to modulate brain states.”
</p>

<p>
Lena marveled at the array of options. She felt powerful, like an
artist with an unlimited palette.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-orgbd9fb67" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="orgbd9fb67"><span class="section-number-2">3.</span> The Exploration</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3">
<p>
Within days, Lena transformed. Her confidence surged, making her an
instant leader at work. The OptoCap’s programs allowed her to adjust
her mood and cognition with a few taps.
</p>

<p>
At home, she selected the "Creative Boost" setting for an upcoming
project. Waves of inspiration washed over her, unlocking ideas she
never imagined.
</p>

<p>
One evening, as she explored deeper into her cap’s settings, Lena
found an unfamiliar program. When she opened it, memories of board
meetings and conversations she didn’t remember participating in
flooded her mind.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-org74d99c7" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org74d99c7"><span class="section-number-2">4.</span> The Revelation</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4">
<p>
Alarmed, Lena contacted Ethan. He arrived quickly, his usual composure
replaced by nervousness.
</p>

<p>
“Lena, I assure you, everything is fine,” he began, but Lena cut him
off.
</p>

<p>
“I found a program logging my thoughts. What is NeuroLight doing?”
</p>

<p>
Ethan hesitated. “There are built-in data collection systems. The
company uses them to monitor user feedback&#x2026;and sometimes influence.”
</p>

<p>
“Influence?” Lena repeated, incredulous. “You mean control.”
</p>

<p>
Ethan nodded, cornered. “It’s part of ensuring compliance and
optimizing the system.”
</p>

<p>
Realization struck Lena—she was being manipulated. Her mind was not
her own.
</p>
</div>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sci-fi" /><category term="shorts" /><category term="optogenetics" /><category term="sci-fi" /><category term="shorts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the near future, NeuroLight Corporation revolutionized neuroscience with a procedure that replaced the top of the human skull with an artificial cap. This "OptoCap" embedded with micro-scale light emitters, allowed precise control over brain activity through optogenetics—a technique that used light to manipulate neurons engineered to be light-sensitive.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The fork</title><link href="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-08-08-the-fork" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The fork" /><published>2024-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/the-fork</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-08-08-the-fork"><![CDATA[<p>
Explore a world reshaped by guided evolution, where a privileged
class challenges traditional norms and steers humanity to unexpected
fates.   
</p>


<p>
<b>Disclaimer: this post was created with ChatGPT, an AI language model.</b>
</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
  <img src="/assets/images/the-fork.png" style="width: 50%">
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orgbce3027" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="orgbce3027"><span class="section-number-2">1.</span> Take 1: Endless forms</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1">
<p>
In the year 2160, the city of Aria stood as a beacon of progress and
unity. Here, the Selected, a privileged class born sterile due to
atypical sex differentiation, had risen to power. For centuries,
they had been marginalized due to their inability to reproduce
traditionally, but with advancements in genetic engineering, they
found a new purpose.
</p>

<p>
The Selected devised a system where offspring were created through a
combination of their original DNA and advanced genetic
engineering. This method allowed the creation of highly adaptive,
intelligent, and emotionally balanced humans who were celebrated as
the "Neo-Gens." The old societal emphasis on sexual reproduction
dwindled, as the Neo-Gens quickly demonstrated extraordinary talents
and harmonious temperaments.
</p>

<p>
With the Selected in leadership positions, they shifted governmental
incentives to focus on intellectual and creative contributions rather
than traditional family structures. Those who excelled in arts,
sciences, and community leadership were rewarded with resources and
opportunities, fostering a society driven by merit and innovation.
</p>

<p>
As decades passed, the city of Aria flourished. Conflicts over
resources diminished, as collaboration became the cornerstone of
society. With genetic diversity and innovation at the forefront,
diseases that plagued the human race for centuries were eradicated,
and the environment thrived under careful stewardship.
</p>

<p>
Elders sat in the serene Gardens of Aria, observing children playing—a
new generation that knew no prejudice or inequality. The Selected
watched with pride, knowing they had not only survived but had
reshaped humanity's fate.
</p>
</div>
</div>



<div id="outline-container-orgede5b5f" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="orgede5b5f"><span class="section-number-2">2.</span> Take 2: The future is sterile</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2">
<p>
By 2160, the Omega Line, once a marginalized class, defined by their
sterility, had seized control of the city of Aria. With
advancements in genetic engineering, they began creating offspring
not through traditional means but by combining their DNA with
engineered enhancements, producing the Neo-Gens.
</p>

<p>
The shift from sexual reproduction to engineered births led
to societal unrest. Traditional families, feeling threatened by the
new system, protested against what they saw as an erosion of human
nature. The government, now dominated by the Omega Line, responded
with strict laws that favored the Neo-Gens, marginalizing those who
clung to old ways.
</p>

<p>
The promise of progress gave way to control. Society split into two
classes: the genetically engineered Neo-Gens and the "Naturals," those
born through traditional reproduction. Naturals faced increasing
discrimination, relegated to menial jobs, and barred from leadership
roles.
</p>

<p>
As the divide deepened, Aria became a city under surveillance, where
dissenters were swiftly silenced. The Omega Line, in their bid to
maintain control, implemented a draconian regime, manipulating
genetics to create a generation of Neo-Gens devoid of free will.
</p>

<p>
Hope flickered among the Naturals, who formed underground resistance
groups, determined to restore the balance and ensure diversity in
human evolution. But the Omega Line's grip was strong, and for every
small victory, the resistance suffered great losses.
</p>

<p>
Life continues in the city as the Omega Line maintains a firm grip
on the government. Stories circulate about Normals walking
among the general population, though no one has had direct contact
with them since the fork.   
</p>
</div>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sci-fi" /><category term="sci-fi" /><category term="shorts" /><category term="diversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore a world reshaped by guided evolution, where a privileged class challenges traditional norms and steers humanity to unexpected fates.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vorherbestimmt von Robert Sapolsky</title><link href="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-04-24-sapolsky-vorherbestimmt" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vorherbestimmt von Robert Sapolsky" /><published>2024-04-24T18:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-24T18:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/sapolsky-vorherbestimmt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-04-24-sapolsky-vorherbestimmt"><![CDATA[<p>
"Vorherbestimmt" ist ein Buch von Robert Sapolsky, in dem der Autor
für den Determinismus argumentiert. 
</p>

<div class="amzn-disclaimer">
  <p>
    <strong>Disclosure:</strong> Some of the links below are affiliate
    links. This means that if you click through and make a purchase, I
    may earn a small commission at no extra cost to you.
  </p>
</div>



<p>
Sapolsky erklärt, dass Freier Wille bedeutet, nicht nur seine eigenen
Handlungen, sondern auch seine eigene Absicht wählen zu können.
</p>

<p>
Eines der bekanntesten Experimente zum Thema Freier Wille sind die
Libet-Experimente, die zeigen, dass Handlungen ausgeführt werden,
bevor man sich ihrer eigenen Handlungen bewusst ist.
</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
  <iframe width="427"
          height="240"
          src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OjCt-L0Ph5o"
          title="The Libet Experiment: Is Free Will Just an Illusion?"
          frameborder="0"
          allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share"
          referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin"
          allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>


<p>
Im Libet-Experiment werden jedoch nur die kurzen Momente vor den
Handlungen analysiert, was Sapolsky als unzureichend empfindet. Laut
Sapolskys Definition von Freiem Willen können wir die entfernten
Ursachen des Verhaltens nicht ignorieren. Das bedeutet, wir müssen
nicht nur die Millisekunden, Minuten und Stunden vor der Handlung
analysieren, sondern auch die vorherigen Jahre, Jahrzehnte,
Jahrhunderte usw. Um etwas als Freien Willen zu bezeichnen, müssen wir
die unverursachte Ursache finden.
</p>

<p>
Nur die unmittelbare Vergangenheit der Handlungen zu betrachten, ist
laut Sapolsky, wie nur die letzten drei Minuten eines Films zu
sehen. Freiem Willen die Anerkennung für seine Handlungen zu geben,
ist ein Eingeständnis, die Ursachen nicht zu kennen.
</p>

<p>
<a href="https://amzn.to/3N1sBTF"
          target="_blank">
         Kauf das Buch bei Amazon
       </a>
</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><category term="deutsch" /><category term="buch" /><category term="sapolsky" /><category term="free-will" /><category term="bio" /><category term="journal" /><category term="deutsch" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA["Vorherbestimmt" ist ein Buch von Robert Sapolsky, in dem der Autor für den Determinismus argumentiert.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eine kurze Geschichte der Intelligenz</title><link href="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-04-20-gehirn+evo+ki" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eine kurze Geschichte der Intelligenz" /><published>2024-04-20T13:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-20T13:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/gehirn+evo+ki</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-04-20-gehirn+evo+ki"><![CDATA[<p>
Gestern habe ich ein sehr cooles Video geschaut. Es handelt von der
Evolution der Intelligenz. Hier ist das Bild, das bei mir im
Gedächtnis geblieben ist.
</p>

<div class="amzn-disclaimer">
  <p>
    <strong>Disclosure:</strong> Some of the links below are affiliate
    links. This means that if you click through and make a purchase, I
    may earn a small commission at no extra cost to you.
  </p>
</div>



<p>
Das Video basiert auf dem Buch von Max Bennet:
<a href="https://amzn.to/3Y2HGuy"
          target="_blank">
         Eine kurze Geschichte der Intelligenz.
       </a>
</p>


<div style="text-align: center">
  <img src="/assets/images/bhi-pyramid.png">
  <figcaption>Evolutionäre Durchbrüche der Intelligenz.</figcaption>
</div>


<p>
Der Erzähler spricht über die Geschichte der Intelligenz aus der
Perspektive der Entwicklung des Gehirns sowie der größten Durchbrüche
bei der Lernfähigkeit. 
</p>

<ol class="org-ol">
<li>Belohnung suchen: Instinktverhalten. Die einfachste Form der
Intelligenz, kein Lernen.</li>
<li>Aus Erfahrung lernen: empirische Erprobung mit Rückkopplung,
Belohnung korrekten Verhaltens, Lernen aus Fehlern, Bestärkendes
Lernen.</li>
<li>Gedankenexperimente: Simulation eigener Handlungen, Planung und
Entscheidungen auf Basis erwarteter (simulierter) zukünftiger
Belohnungen.</li>
<li>Theorie des Mentalen: Simulation der Gedanken einer anderen Person,
Lernen aus den Fehlern anderer.</li>
<li>Sprache: Externalisierung von Gedanken oder Ideen, Lernen
unabhängig von Handlungen.</li>
</ol>


<p>
Das vollständige Video kannst du auf YouTube ansehen:
</p>

<iframe width="800" height="600"
        src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5EcQ1IcEMFQ"
        title="How Intelligence Evolved | A 600 Million Year Story"
        frameborder="0"
        allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share"
        referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin"
        allowfullscreen>
</iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><category term="deutsch" /><category term="journal" /><category term="deutsch" /><category term="ai" /><category term="ki" /><category term="intelligence" /><category term="intelligenz" /><category term="überprüfen" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Gestern habe ich ein sehr cooles Video geschaut. Es handelt von der Evolution der Intelligenz. Hier ist das Bild, das bei mir im Gedächtnis geblieben ist.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Der Anschein von Fairness</title><link href="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-02-10-der-anschein-von-fairness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Der Anschein von Fairness" /><published>2024-02-10T11:19:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-10T11:19:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/der-anschein-von-fairness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pgpbpadilla.github.io/2024-02-10-der-anschein-von-fairness"><![CDATA[<p>
Ich höre gerade das Hörbuch von Richard Thaler, <i><a href="https://w.wiki/98p9">Misbehaving</a></i>
(Fehlverhalten). Im Kapitel 14: "What seems fair" (Was fair erscheint)
beschreibt der Autor einige Situationen, in denen eine Firma
Entscheidungen darüber trifft, wie Preise festgelegt werden sollen,
und wie die Kunden darauf reagiert haben.
</p>

<div class="amzn-disclaimer">
  <p>
    <strong>Disclosure:</strong> Some of the links below are affiliate
    links. This means that if you click through and make a purchase, I
    may earn a small commission at no extra cost to you.
  </p>
</div>



<p>
Das erste Beispiel bezieht sich auf die Preise für Schnee-schaufeln
nach einem schweren Schneefall. Die Firma hat sich entschieden, die
Preise zu erhöhen. Der Grund dafür war, dass bei höherer Nachfrage die
Schaufeln knapp werden und es allgemein bekannt ist, dass Preise
steigen, wenn die Nachfrage hoch und das Angebot niedrig ist.
</p>

<p>
Die wiederkehrende Bemerkung im gesamten Buch ist, dass, wenn Menschen
als rationale Agenten (Econs) betrachtet werden, Fehler im gesunden
Menschenverstand auftreten können, z.B. würde der durchschnittliche
Mensch die Entscheidung der Firma im obigen Beispiel als ungerecht
beurteilen.
</p>

<p>
<a href="https://amzn.to/47Sdgyo"
          target="_blank">
         Kauf das Buch bei Amazon.
       </a>
</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="journal" /><category term="deutsch" /><category term="journal" /><category term="deutsch" /><category term="econ" /><category term="thaler" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ich höre gerade das Hörbuch von Richard Thaler, Misbehaving (Fehlverhalten). Im Kapitel 14: "What seems fair" (Was fair erscheint) beschreibt der Autor einige Situationen, in denen eine Firma Entscheidungen darüber trifft, wie Preise festgelegt werden sollen, und wie die Kunden darauf reagiert haben.]]></summary></entry></feed>